<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>academic writing on Wu Sun, Ph.D.</title>
    <link>http://wusun.name/tags/academic-writing/</link>
    <description>Recent content in academic writing on Wu Sun, Ph.D.</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Jul 2018 20:32:00 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://wusun.name/tags/academic-writing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>A comparison of some markdown publishing systems</title>
      <link>http://wusun.name/blog/2018-07-16-markdown-publishing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jul 2018 20:32:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://wusun.name/blog/2018-07-16-markdown-publishing/</guid>
      <description>Markdown is the new LaTeX for technical and academic writing. Although LaTeX is still the gold standard, if your writing does not involve a whole lot of theorems and proofs, drawing diagrams in TikZ and PGF, or some heavy tweaking of the page styles, Markdown may suffice for your use cases. A lightly marked text format like Markdown helps the writer concentrate on the contents rather than the styles.
In the past few years, I have gradually replaced some of my writing tasks in LaTeX with automated generation of LaTeX and PDF from Markdown by pandoc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Merge multiple EPS subfigures into a single figure using LaTeX Beamer</title>
      <link>http://wusun.name/blog/2015-05-13-merge-figure/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://wusun.name/blog/2015-05-13-merge-figure/</guid>
      <description>Some academic journals require all subfigures to be combined as one single file for submission. This may not be easy to do if you don&amp;rsquo;t have a professional software (often proprietary) to edit vector maps, e.g., EPS and PDF.
I found a convenient way to deal with in LaTeX Beamer. The idea is to create a beamer slide and insert your subfigures with the command \includegraphics{} in the same figure environment.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>